Mayur Vishwasrao

Address: Pune

Email: mayurvishwasrao6@gmail.com

Mob: +91-8208253383

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Experienced data scientist having 4+ years of experience in Machine learning, Deep learning, and NLP with demonstrated history of working in the industries like, Oil & energy, Healthcare, Banking & Finance, Legal, Retail, Telecom, etc.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

May. 2017 – Present Pune

Lead Engineer, HCL Technologies

- Built a generative based conversational Chatbot using deep learning models such as Seq2seq, RNN, and LSTM for telecom client
- Worked on Short Text Summarization using Naïve Bayes model for healthcare client
- Developed a HR analytics tools for HCL internal recruitment team using Rshiny
- Built a binary classification model using Bi-LSTM model for healthcare client
- Text classification using machine-learning algorithms such as Random forest, SVM, Naïve Bayes etc.
- Working on Voice Chatbots using google cloud speech API, and LSTM architecture
- Extensive Knowledge of NLP techniques such as POS tagging, Lemmatization, NER, stemming, Tokenization, word2vec (Skip-gram, Continuous bag of word), glove embeddings
- Extensive knowledge of using Machine Learning techniques such as Decision tree, SVM, Random forest, Ordinary Least Squares, Logistic regression, k-Nearest Neighbour, CHAID, Clustering etc. in R, Python
- Extensive knowledge of Deep learning models such as seq2seq, LSTM, LSTM with attention, Bi-Directional LSTM, GRU, with tensor flow framework

Dec. 2016 – Apr. 2017 Pune

Machine Learning Engineer, Futurism Technologies Pvt Ltd

- Developed a conversational Chatbot using deep learning models- Seq2seq, LSTM, and GRU
- Built an automated email auto responder system using LSTM with Attention layer model
- Churn prediction using Logistic Regression

May. 2015 – Oct. 2016 Pune

Data Scientist, BancTec TPS India Pvt. Ltd

- Identify business problems, translate it into analytical framework and propose a structured solution in line with business objective
- Built a highly accurate, user friendly, energy-forecasting platform for a power-supply client company to use across all of their market areas
- Developed an Energy consumption forecasting model using Multiple linear regression in R
- Built algorithms using Natural Language Processing (NLP) for Data Extraction
- Built models for data and fields extraction using machine learning for legal, healthcare, and banking domain
- Text processing and Information Extraction using R programming and Python Technology
- Worked on Predictive analytics projects in python using pandas, Scikit-learn, Nltk, Numpy, and Scipy libraries

 Communicate findings clearly to both technical & non-technical audiences to approach a business challenge

Dec. 2013 – May. 2015 Pune

- Research Analyst, CRISIL Pvt Ltd
 - Forecasted quarterly sales of manufacturing firms using time series models using SAS tool
 - Worked on model validation projects for different banks in the US
 - Sound Knowledge of extracting data using different API's (Application Programming Interface) for data analysis for e.g. Twitter API, from where data is extracted for predictive analytics models
 - Worked on Python with projects such as Sentiments Analysis of Social Media Websites like Twitter, Facebook, and movie review analysis using Twitter, Facebook, and Rotten Tomatoes databases
 - Maintained database for voluntary insurance market of the US and providing direct comparison of client's product offering vis-à-vis competitors
 - Performed competitive and premium pricing analysis of insurance companies in the US for voluntary worksite group products. Also indexed and maintained database of insurance companies' disclosures
 - Worked on special projects such as Sentimental Analysis of India Budget 2014-15
 - Company profiles: Worked out detailed profiles, comprising overview, financials, geography, products and management, and prepared newsletters to track industries on a regular basis, capturing developments such as product launch, management changes, expansion or divestment etc.

EDUCATION

Aug. 2015 • Msc (Financial Economics)

• Gokhale Institute of Politics & Economics - Pune

Jul. 2013 Bsc (Statistics)

• Pune University - Pune

SKILLS

Experienced • Python

Experienced • R-Software

Experienced Supervised Machine Learning: Linear/Logistic/Polynomial/Lasso/Ridge Regression
Techniques, Decision Tree, Support Vector Machine, Random Forest, Naive Bayes, KNN

Experienced • Unsupervised Machine Learning: K-means Clustering, Hierarchical Clustering

Experienced • Deep Learning: RNN, LSTM, Seq2Seq, Bi-LSTM

Skillful • NLP: POS Tagging, Lemmatization, Tokenization, Chunking, NER, etc.

Experienced • Advanced Forecasting Methodologies: AR, MA, ARMA, ARIMA

Beginner • SQL

Skillful • Data Visualization

Skillful • Other Skills: SAS, Weka, E-views, MS Excel

CERTIFICATIONS

- NSE (National Stock Exchange) Certified Capital Market Professional Module
- Certified Financial Modelling in MS-Excel